I was really blown away by this
randomized control trial showing clearly
and convincingly that bourberine
supplementation reduced the risk of
cancer directly. I was excited then and
I'm excited now. But now for different
reasons because now that we have the
clinical data in hand, I could get more
into some of the additional studies
related to bourberine and cancer like
these.
These studies describe in detail two
different ways by which bourberin
protects us from colarctal cancer. So
allow me to fascinate you with what
happens to your body when you take such
a simple unassuming supplement. This
molecule bourberine comes from the
barberry plant primarily and researchers
showed recently that when people
supplement with it they have a
noticeably reduced risk of what's known
as adenomomas. These are abnormal
growths in your colon. The thing is
these growths are far more likely to
turn into fullblown cancer, colurectal
cancer. Now, there's a reason that we
screen for colurectal cancer. We have to
check for these abnormal growths.
Anyway, I won't rehash the details of
the previous analysis, but just know
that the results were a impressive and b
directly applicable to you and me. Then
exactly how does bourbon enact these
impressive results? Well, one of them is
through changing what's called the micro
environment of your colon shown in this
study. When you're healthy, your colon
is filled with billions of bacteria and
viruses that ultimately lend themselves
to a healthier you. Now, I get that when
you hear the word virus and bacteria,
you might think, uh, what? But there are
actually many strains of each that are
neutral or even beneficial to our
health. All part of what's called the
microbiome. Well, when we take
microbiome samples from people who are
healthy, people with these precancerous
adenomas, remember that's the abnormal
growth and people with already present
colurectal cancer, we see significant
differences in the makeup of the
microbiome. That said, in previous
studies, a particular bacterium called
fuso bacterium nucleatum, which I'm
going to abbreviate FN, is especially
prominent in colctal cancer. So, the
researchers did something clever. They
took mice that have a genetic
predisposition for cancer and seeded.
So, meaning that they implanted effice
with and without bourberin. We see that
here. The left image is of excise
colons. The top is of the one without
the addition of the cancer associated
bacterium and the bottom one is with.
Now it's tough to see, but the bottom
one has some growth in it. Those are
tumors. The right graph is more telling
though. Essentially, if the lines in
dots go up, that's more tumors. I
suppose you can guess if that's good or
bad.
It's bad. The FN condition on the right
is noticeably elevated. This proves
causation as in the presence of these
bacteria increases colurectal tumors,
cancer. Now for the real treat though,
notice the far right condition there,
the one with the BBR included. That's
our lovely bourberin. Notice how it
knocks cancer back down. That's because
the bourberine is enacting its cancer
protective role. The main point here is
two things. So one shifts in the
microbiome the colon micro environment
promotes cancer and two bourberine
inhibits this microbiome shift thereby
protecting against this cancer. That
alone is a remarkable discovery. But if
you follow through the cancer literature
for a minute you'll notice some themes.
One of these themes is that the reliance
of cancer on glucose sugar. Now I've
covered this in the past several times.
However, it may also apply here as well.
We can see that as clearly as my pasty
white skin right here. The top graph
indicates the amount of glucose taken up
by colon cancer cells as concentration
of bourbon is increased in a step-wise
fashion. Now, I mean just look at that
data. As bourbon concentration
increases, glucose uptake by the cells
is impaired. However, even more telling
is in this context is looking at the
cell viability, meaning how well the
cancer cells survive under the same
scenario. The lower the line goes, the
fewer colon cancer cells survive. A good
thing. Now, to be clear, we're looking
at isolated cells. And while we can say
that bourberine has a direct colon
cancer inhibiting effect here, we can't
technically assume the reduction in
glucose is the reason for that we would
need further experiments. But I'll let
you in on a not so little secret. They
did that too. And they showed more
evidence that bourberine inhibits the
glucose metabolism in colarctal cancer
cells. So the point here is that bourber
not only inhibits through indirect
mechanisms like the impact on the
microbiome but also direct inhibition of
the glucose metabolism of colarctal
cancer cells. That's pretty incredible,
isn't it? So now across four mechanistic
studies and two analyses based on
randomized control trials, we have this
mounting evidence that simply
supplementing with bourberine can reduce
our colctal cancer risk through multiple
mechanisms. So, how would I approach all
this? I'll get into how to apply this,
but you may have noticed that there's
much more to cover like the remarkable
mechanisms inside the cells like the
jack stat pathway, the blockage of the
signaling proteins like Hif one, and
even some unique effects on metabolism
enzymes called pyuvate kynise and even
what else happens to the microbiome
after this fuso bacterium nucleatum
takes hold. The point is there's a lot
more complexity that I glossed over. So,
if you're looking for the full version,
all the details included, then check out
the extended version of this video that
you're currently watching. It's included
with an accompanying article I do with
all my full videos, all of these perks
right over here, including a master
supplement guide that covers multiple
vetted sources of bourberin, and
honestly, many other perks. Where to
find all this, you may ask? It's all in
the first link in the description. Just
join the Physionic Insiders. It's my
premium research platform. And now back
to application.
Here's how I'd approach this. If you
have a family history of colorctal
cancer, it likely is a good idea to
consider supplementation with bourberin.
However, if you don't have a family
history or personal history, the
suggestion weakens somewhat. Now, it'll
just depend on your want to invest into
supplements. The reality is that there
are many things that affect colurectal
cancer risk. So I don't want you
thinking that bourburn is the one and
only cure. It isn't. Though I am excited
about the research. If you did decide to
supplement, the total dose used in the
randomized control trials is 600 millig
that's split into two doses and it was
consumed long-term. So we're talking
several years. But honestly, instead of
me restating some of the nuances that
I've already covered in the past, then
check out my more in-depth breakdown
right here. Or if you're looking for
other nutrients that protect against
cancer, then check out this sucker right
here. Thanks a ton for hanging out with
me. I hope you found this as impressive
and exciting as I did. I'm genuinely
curious where the state of the research
will be in a few years. I'll keep my
ears open. Catch you in the next one.
See youa.